<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
        <title>Alex Angas</title>
        <description>Alex Angas - Alex Angas</description>
        <link>http://alexangas.github.io</link>
        <link>http://alexangas.github.io</link>
        <lastBuildDate>2013-09-26T02:33:46+01:00</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>2013-09-26T02:33:46+01:00</pubDate>
        <ttl>1800</ttl>


        <item>
                <title>SQL Server index tuning flavoured with Entity Framework and WCF Data Services</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m working on a particularly database intensive application at the moment. We use Entity Framework code first for our back-end database reads and writes, and have a WCF Data Services wrapper for REST read access from the UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks as load has increased I&amp;#8217;ve started noticing the occasional SQL deadlock and timeout on production. Suddenly yesterday we reached some sort of tipping point and were inundated with timeouts. The cause of most of these was found just by running SQL Profiler and watching some unnecessary queries spill down the screen (multiple functions inside a view, bad idea). Once the chaos was largely over, I started looking at whether our database indexes were actually useful and how to verify this with EF and WCF DS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;configuring-sql-profiler-for-entity-framework&quot;&gt;Configuring SQL Profiler for Entity Framework&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the SQL Profiler settings I found worked best to capture both EF and WCF DS queries (with Show All Columns ticked):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SP:StmtCompleted&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SP:StmtStarting&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SQL:BatchCompleted&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SQL:BatchStarting&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This combination allows you to see CPU time and how long statements took, as well as then letting you load the trace into Database Tuning Advisor (DTA). If you want to check for timeouts and deadlocks as well, make sure you include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deadlock graph&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lock:Deadlock&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lock:Deadlock Chain&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lock:Timeout (timeout &amp;gt; 0)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/TraceProperties.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the Database Tuning Advisor, it specifically &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms190957%28v=sql.105%29&quot;&gt;requires&lt;/a&gt; SQL:BatchCompleted and SP:StmtCompleted. The details of how to get that running &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms178095%28v=sql.105%29&quot;&gt;is on MSDN&lt;/a&gt;. Set the SQL Profiler trace to output to a file (if you want to analyse on your local machine) or database table. Let it run for a few hours while the tasks you want to optimise are being performed by your users. If you&amp;#8217;re game you can run this on production for more accurate results, but a test environment is preferred provided you can recreate a typical load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;analyzing-sql-profiler-results-in-the-database-tuning-advisor&quot;&gt;Analyzing SQL Profiler results in the Database Tuning Advisor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the most useful things from the DTA are the SQL script of recommendations in combination with the &amp;#8220;Index usage report (recommended)&amp;#8221;. These will get you 90% of the way to some quick optimizations. After running the DTA, save the SQL script from the Actions / Save Recommendations menu. Then switch over to the Reports tab, choose the report just mentioned, and then right-click on the table of results and click &amp;#8220;Export To File&amp;#8221; (this feature is not obvious!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy both files over to your local machine. Open the script in a text editor, and use Excel to open the XML report. Sort by &amp;#8220;PercentUsage&amp;#8221; and look at how the indexes you already have compare with the DTA recommendations (that start with _dta_index). You can easily find its recommended indexes in the SQL script and adapt them to your needs - just give them good names! Also consider dropping the indexes that don&amp;#8217;t show up at all as each database write usually causes an update of the index which can take time and cause further timeout issues.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2012/08/sql-server-index-tuning-entity-framework-wcf-data-services</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2012/08/sql-server-index-tuning-entity-framework-wcf-data-services</guid>
                <pubDate>2012-08-22T10:20:10+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Jekyll Introduction</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;This Jekyll introduction will outline specifically  what Jekyll is and why you would want to use it.
Directly following the intro we&amp;#8217;ll learn exactly &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; Jekyll does what it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-jekyll&quot;&gt;What is Jekyll?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a parsing engine bundled as a ruby gem used to build static websites from
dynamic components such as templates, partials, liquid code, markdown, etc. Jekyll is known as &amp;#8220;a simple, blog aware, static site generator&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website is created with Jekyll. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Sites&quot;&gt;Other Jekyll websites&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-jekyll-do&quot;&gt;What does Jekyll Do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a ruby gem you install on your local system.
Once there you can call &lt;code&gt;jekyll --server&lt;/code&gt; on a directory and provided that directory
is setup in a way jekyll expects, it will do magic stuff like parse markdown/textile files, 
compute categories, tags, permalinks, and construct your pages from layout templates and partials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once parsed, Jekyll stores the result in a self-contained static &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; folder.
The intention here is that you can serve all contents in this folder statically from a plain static web-server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can think of Jekyll as a normalish dynamic blog but rather than parsing content, templates, and tags
on each request, Jekyll does this once &lt;em&gt;beforehand&lt;/em&gt; and caches the &lt;em&gt;entire website&lt;/em&gt; in a folder for serving statically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jekyll-is-not-blogging-software&quot;&gt;Jekyll is Not Blogging Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll is a parsing engine.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll does not come with any content nor does it have any templates or design elements.
This is a common source of confusion when getting started.
Jekyll does not come with anything you actually use or see on your website - you have to make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-should-i-care&quot;&gt;Why Should I Care?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is very minimalistic and very efficient.
The most important thing to realize about Jekyll is that it creates a static representation of your website requiring only a static web-server.
Traditional dynamic blogs like Wordpress require a database and server-side code.
Heavily trafficked dynamic blogs must employ a caching layer that ultimately performs the same job Jekyll sets out to do; serve static content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore if you like to keep things simple and you prefer the command-line over an admin panel UI then give Jekyll a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers like Jekyll because we can write content like we write code:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to write content in markdown or textile in your favorite text-editor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to write and preview your content via localhost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No internet connection required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to publish via git.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to host your blog on a static web-server.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to host freely on GitHub Pages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No database required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-jekyll-works&quot;&gt;How Jekyll Works&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a complete but concise outline of exactly how Jekyll works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be aware that core concepts are introduced in rapid succession without code examples.
This information is not intended to specifically teach you how to do anything, rather it
is intended to give you the &lt;em&gt;full picture&lt;/em&gt; relative to what is going on in Jekyll-world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning these core concepts should help you avoid common frustrations and ultimately 
help you better understand the code examples contained throughout Jekyll-Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-setup&quot;&gt;Initial Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/index.html#start-now&quot;&gt;installing jekyll&lt;/a&gt; you&amp;#8217;ll need to format your website directory in a way jekyll expects.
Jekyll-bootstrap conveniently provides the base directory format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-jekyll-application-base-format&quot;&gt;The Jekyll Application Base Format&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll expects your website directory to be laid out like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
|-- _config.yml
|-- _includes
|-- _layouts
|   |-- default.html
|   |-- post.html
|-- _posts
|   |-- 2011-10-25-open-source-is-good.markdown
|   |-- 2011-04-26-hello-world.markdown
|-- _site
|-- index.html
|-- assets
    |-- css
        |-- style.css
    |-- javascripts
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_config.yml&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  Stores configuration data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_includes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  This folder is for partial views.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_layouts&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  This folder is for the main templates your content will be inserted into.
  You can have different layouts for different pages or page sections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  This folder contains your dynamic content/posts.
  the naming format is required to be &lt;code&gt;@YEAR-MONTH-DATE-title.MARKUP@&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_site&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  This is where the generated site will be placed once Jekyll is done transforming it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;assets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  This folder is not part of the standard jekyll structure.
  The assets folder represents &lt;em&gt;any generic&lt;/em&gt; folder you happen to create in your root directory.
  Directories and files not properly formatted for jekyll will be left untouched for you to serve normally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(read more: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Usage&quot;&gt;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Usage&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jekyll-configuration&quot;&gt;Jekyll Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll supports various configuration options that are fully outlined here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Configuration&quot;&gt;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Configuration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-in-jekyll&quot;&gt;Content in Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content in Jekyll is either a post or a page.
These content &amp;#8220;objects&amp;#8221; get inserted into one or more templates to build the final output for its respective static-page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;posts-and-pages&quot;&gt;Posts and Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both posts and pages should be written in markdown, textile, or HTML and may also contain Liquid templating syntax.
Both posts and pages can have meta-data assigned on a per-page basis such as title, url path, as well as arbitrary custom meta-data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-with-posts&quot;&gt;Working With Posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a Post&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Posts are created by properly formatting a file and placing it the &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formatting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A post must have a valid filename in the form &lt;code&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DATE-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; and be placed in the &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. 
If the data format is invalid Jekyll will not recognize the file as a post. The date and title are automatically parsed from the filename of the post file.
Additionally, each file must have &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/YAML-Front-Matter&quot;&gt;YAML Front-Matter&lt;/a&gt; prepended to its content.
YAML Front-Matter is a valid YAML syntax specifying meta-data for the given file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ordering is an important part of Jekyll but it is hard to specify a custom ordering strategy.
Only reverse chronological and chronological ordering is supported in Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the date is hard-coded into the filename format, to change the order, you must change the dates in the filenames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tags&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Posts can have tags associated with them as part of their meta-data.
Tags may be placed on posts by providing them in the post&amp;#8217;s YAML front matter.
You have access to the post-specific tags in the templates. These tags also get added to the sitewide collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Categories&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Posts may be categorized by providing one or more categories in the YAML front matter.
Categories offer more significance over tags in that they can be reflected in the URL path to the given post.
Note categories in Jekyll work in a specific way.
If you define more than one category you are defining a category hierarchy &amp;#8220;set&amp;#8221;.
Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title :  Hello World
categories : [lessons, beginner]
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defines the category hierarchy &amp;#8220;lessons/beginner&amp;#8221;. Note this is &lt;em&gt;one category&lt;/em&gt; node in Jekyll.
You won&amp;#8217;t find &amp;#8220;lessons&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;beginner&amp;#8221; as two separate categories unless you define them elsewhere as singular categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-with-pages&quot;&gt;Working With Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a Page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pages are created by properly formatting a file and placing it anywhere in the root directory or subdirectories that do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; start with an underscore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formatting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order to register as a Jekyll page the file must contain &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/YAML-Front-Matter&quot;&gt;YAML Front-Matter&lt;/a&gt;.
Registering a page means 1) that Jekyll will process the page and 2) that the page object will be available in the &lt;code&gt;site.pages&lt;/code&gt; array for inclusion into your templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Categories and Tags&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pages do not compute categories nor tags so defining them will have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sub-Directories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If pages are defined in sub-directories, the path to the page will be reflected in the url.
Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
|-- people
    |-- bob
        |-- essay.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page will be available at &lt;code&gt;http://yourdomain.com/people/bob/essay.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended Pages&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;index.html&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will always want to define the root index.html page as this will display on your root URL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;404.html&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Create a root 404.html page and GitHub Pages will serve it as your 404 response.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sitemap.html&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Generating a sitemap is good practice for SEO.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;about.html&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A nice about page is easy to do and gives the human perspective to your website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;templates-in-jekyll&quot;&gt;Templates in Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Templates are used to contain a page&amp;#8217;s or post&amp;#8217;s content.
All templates have access to a global site object variable: &lt;code&gt;site&lt;/code&gt; as well as a page object variable: &lt;code&gt;page&lt;/code&gt;.
The site variable holds all accessible content and metadata relative to the site.
The page variable holds accessible data for the given page or post being rendered at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a Template&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Templates are created by properly formatting a file and placing it in the &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formatting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Templates should be coded in HTML and contain YAML Front Matter. 
All templates can contain Liquid code to work with your site&amp;#8217;s data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rending Page/Post Content in a Template&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is a special variable in all templates named : &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt;.
The &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; variable holds the page/post content including any sub-template content previously defined.
Render the content variable wherever you want your main content to be injected into your template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;...
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&quot;sidebar&quot;&amp;gt; ... &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&quot;main&quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;#123;{content}&amp;#125;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sub-templates&quot;&gt;Sub-Templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sub-templates are exactly templates with the only difference being they 
define another &amp;#8220;root&amp;#8221; layout/template within their YAML Front Matter.
This essentially means a template will render inside of another template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;includes&quot;&gt;Includes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jekyll you can define include files by placing them in the &lt;code&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; folder.
Includes are NOT templates, rather they are just code snippets that get included into templates.
In this way, you can treat the code inside includes as if it was native to the parent template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any valid template code may be used in includes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-liquid-for-templating&quot;&gt;Using Liquid for Templating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Templating is perhaps the most confusing and frustrating part of Jekyll.
This is mainly due to the fact that Jekyll templates must use the Liquid Templating Language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-liquid&quot;&gt;What is Liquid?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt; is a secure templating language developed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://shopify.com&quot;&gt;Shopify&lt;/a&gt;.
Liquid is designed for end-users to be able to execute logic within template files 
without imposing any security risk on the hosting server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll uses Liquid to generate the post content within the final page layout structure and as the primary interface for working with
your site and post/page data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-we-have-to-use-liquid&quot;&gt;Why Do We Have to Use Liquid?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub uses Jekyll to power &lt;a href=&quot;http://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. 
GitHub cannot afford to run arbitrary code on their servers so they lock developers down via Liquid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;liquid-is-not-programmer-friendly&quot;&gt;Liquid is Not Programmer-Friendly.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is liquid is not real code and its not intended to execute real code.
The point being you can&amp;#8217;t do jackshit in liquid that hasn&amp;#8217;t been allowed explicitly by the implementation.
What&amp;#8217;s more you can only access data-structures that have been explicitly passed to the template. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Jekyll&amp;#8217;s case it is not possible to alter what is passed to Liquid without hacking the gem or running custom plugins. 
Both of which cannot be supported by GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a programmer - this is very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But rather than look a gift horse in the mouth we are going to 
suck it up and view it as an opportunity to work around limitations and adopt client-side solutions when possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aside&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
My personal stance is to not invest time trying to hack liquid. It&amp;#8217;s really unnecessary
&lt;em&gt;from a programmer&amp;#8217;s&lt;/em&gt; perspective. That is to say if you have the ability to run custom plugins (i.e. run arbitrary ruby code)
you are better off sticking with ruby. Toward that end I&amp;#8217;ve built &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/plusjade/mustache-with-jekyll&quot;&gt;Mustache-with-Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-assets&quot;&gt;Static Assets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static assets are any file in the root or non-underscored subfolders that are not pages.
That is they have no valid YAML Front Matter and are thus not treated as Jekyll Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static assets should be used for images, css, and javascript files. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-jekyll-parses-files&quot;&gt;How Jekyll Parses Files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember Jekyll is a processing engine. There are two main types of parsing in Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content parsing.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  This is done with textile or markdown.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Template parsing.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
This is done with the liquid templating language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thus there are two main types of file formats needed for this parsing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post and Page files.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All content in Jekyll is either a post or a page so valid posts and pages are parsed with markdown or textile.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Template files.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
  These files go in &lt;code&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; folder and contain your blogs &lt;strong&gt;templates&lt;/strong&gt;. They should be made in HTML with the help of Liquid syntax.
  Since include files are simply injected into templates they are essentially parsed as if they were native to the template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arbitrary files and folders.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Files that &lt;em&gt;are not&lt;/em&gt; valid pages are treated as static content and pass through 
Jekyll untouched and reside on your blog in the exact structure and format they originally existed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;formatting-files-for-parsing&quot;&gt;Formatting Files for Parsing.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve outlined the need for valid formatting using &lt;strong&gt;YAML Front Matter&lt;/strong&gt;.
Templates, posts, and pages all need to provide valid YAML Front Matter even if the Matter is empty.
This is the only way Jekyll knows you want the file processed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YAML Front Matter must be prepended to the top of template/post/page files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
layout: post
category : pages
tags : [how-to, jekyll]
---

... contents ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three hyphens on a new line start the Front-Matter block and three hyphens on a new line end the block.
The data inside the block must be valid YAML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Configuration parameters for YAML Front-Matter is outlined here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/YAML-Front-Matter&quot;&gt;A comprehensive explanation of YAML Front Matter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;defining-layouts-for-posts-and-templates-parsing&quot;&gt;Defining Layouts for Posts and Templates Parsing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the YAML Front Matter defines the template file for which the given post or template should be injected into.
If a template file specifies its own layout, it is effectively being used as a &lt;code&gt;sub-template.&lt;/code&gt;
That is to say loading a post file into a template file that refers to another template file with work in the way you&amp;#8217;d expect; as a nested sub-template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-jekyll-generates-the-final-static-files&quot;&gt;How Jekyll Generates the Final Static Files.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Jekyll&amp;#8217;s job is to generate a static representation of your website. 
The following is an outline of how that&amp;#8217;s done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll collects data.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  Jekyll scans the posts directory and collects all posts files as post objects. It then scans the layout assets and collects those and finally scans other directories in search of pages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll computes data.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  Jekyll takes these objects, computes metadata (permalinks, tags, categories, titles, dates) from them and constructs one 
  big &lt;code&gt;site&lt;/code&gt; object that holds all the posts, pages, layouts, and respective metadata.
  At this stage your site is one big computed ruby object.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll liquifies posts and templates.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  Next jekyll loops through each post file and converts (through markdown or textile) and &lt;strong&gt;liquifies&lt;/strong&gt; the post inside of its respective layout(s).
  Once the post is parsed and liquified inside the the proper layout structure, the layout itself is &amp;#8220;liquified&amp;#8221;. &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Liquification&lt;/strong&gt; is defined as follows: Jekyll initiates a Liquid template, and passes a simpler hash representation of the ruby site object as well as a simpler
  hash representation of the ruby post object. These simplified data structures are what you have access to in the templates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll generates output.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
 Finally the liquid templates are &amp;#8220;rendered&amp;#8221;, thereby processing any liquid syntax provided in the templates
 and saving the final, static representation of the file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Because Jekyll computes the entire site in one fell swoop, each template is given access to 
a global &lt;code&gt;site&lt;/code&gt; hash that contains useful data. It is this data that you&amp;#8217;ll iterate through and format 
using the Liquid tags and filters in order to render it onto a given page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, in Jekyll you are an end-user. Your API has only two components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The manner in which you setup your directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The liquid syntax and variables passed into the liquid templates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the data objects available to you in the templates via Liquid are outlined in the &lt;strong&gt;API Section&lt;/strong&gt; of Jekyll-Bootstrap.
You can also read the original documentation here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Template-Data&quot;&gt;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Template-Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this paints a clearer picture of what Jekyll is doing and why it works the way it does.
As noted, our main programming constraint is the fact that our API is limited to what is accessible via Liquid and Liquid only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll-bootstrap is intended to provide helper methods and strategies aimed at making it more intuitive and easier to work with Jekyll =)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;/strong&gt; for reading this far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please take a look at []() 
or jump right into &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Usage&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#8217;d like.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/12/jekyll-introduction</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/12/jekyll-introduction</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Do your research before developing with InfoPath</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: When I first drafted this post back in May 2011 I was not aware that our sister company was developing a competitor to InfoPath. When I did find out, I couldn&amp;#8217;t say anything due to NDA. I&amp;#8217;ve held off publishing this until that product&amp;#8217;s been announced in order to be as transparent as possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve worked on numerous InfoPath projects over the last two years, covering each version – 2003, 2007 and 2010. As time has gone on, I&amp;#8217;ve started to develop a twitch whenever someone mentions &amp;#8220;InfoPath&amp;#8221;. Now to be clear, the product has its place and there are times when it is appropriate for use. However there are also things to be &lt;strong&gt;very cautious of&lt;/strong&gt;, even to the point where alternatives should be considered such as custom development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve tried to tone down this post, but there is a fair bit of frustration here that is hard to eradicate! Here&amp;#8217;s my top list of gotchas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;business-logic-is-hidden&quot;&gt;Business logic is hidden&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default way that InfoPath names its data structures as a user creates them looks like this: &lt;code&gt;field23&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;group22&lt;/code&gt;. The UI never encourages the user to give fields names that describe their purpose. You could argue it actively discourages it by introducing the friction of of a dialog before a field can be renamed. It would be nice if a field was in &amp;#8220;rename mode&amp;#8221; when a control associated with it was first dragged onto the form!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add behaviour to a form, the user attaches &amp;#8220;rules&amp;#8221; to fields. This is an &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; rules to &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; field relationship. As it&amp;#8217;s not unusual to complete the design of a form with up to 50 or even many more fields, many of these rules make up the end result, spread throughout the form. This causes serious maintenance difficulties as the only good UI for finding and working on these rules is on a per-field basis. There is a Logic Inspector &amp;#8220;feature&amp;#8221; provided with InfoPath but its UI is very poorly designed and there&amp;#8217;s no way to relate rules to each other. This makes it easy to forget what a rule is there for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using InfoPath seems like such an easy solution. In just a few clicks you can have a very powerful form without thinking about it! And therein lies the rub. I&amp;#8217;d argue that many people don&amp;#8217;t put in the effort to properly think through the design of a form, and wind up with unwieldy beasts of complexity. InfoPath provides no assistance in making a form self-documenting and expects you to remember what &lt;code&gt;field23&lt;/code&gt; is for, or &lt;code&gt;Rule 5&lt;/code&gt;. Over time we can end up with no-one really knowing how the thing is supposed to work, and forced to unravel a web of rules and fields to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-loaded-gun-feature---custom-code&quot;&gt;The loaded gun feature - custom code&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most innocent of requirements can require custom code and sometimes aren&amp;#8217;t discovered until later down the track once a form has been largely developed and you&amp;#8217;re locked in to the InfoPath platform. The problem with code is that it requires a developer, adds another level of complexity, and changes the deployment method to SharePoint entirely (requiring involvement from the IT department&amp;#8217;s SharePoint administrator). Adding code is something that &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/infopath/archive/2011/04/14/working-with-vsto-2008-projects-in-infopath-2010.aspx&quot;&gt;even Microsoft don&amp;#8217;t recommend&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Create InfoPath forms with as little code as possible, and put the bulk of your code into middle tier services and workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re adding code anyway, think about &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; you are using InfoPath and not developing a custom solution. If your deployment target is SharePoint, newer features such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee535491.aspx&quot;&gt;LINQ to SharePoint&lt;/a&gt; are very easy to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;do-you-prefer-a-messy-or-broken-form&quot;&gt;Do you prefer a messy or broken form?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have developed a form and decide one part of it has to be deleted or replaced with something else then you have two options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can leave the old fields and groups unused in the underlying data structure but not show them. This means over time you&amp;#8217;ll have leftover cruft with a purpose that no-one can remember.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can delete them and break the ability to open any older forms. Removing aspects of the data structure is a strict no-no and InfoPath cannot handle this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-multiple-environment-nightmare&quot;&gt;The multiple environment nightmare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;InfoPath loves to hard-code references to everything, particularly data sources, so if you want to follow a best practice process of deploying to a test environment first, you&amp;#8217;re asking for more maintenance headaches. Some of the issues are alleviated by deploying a form as a feature that can dynamically correct these references but this requires Visual Studio and locks you into this method of deployment for the life of the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;#8217;s the way republishing the same form across multiple environments will almost certainly cause confusion to both you and SharePoint as column names are not kept identical. This is an issue documented in Microsoft KB article &lt;a href=&quot;http://support.microsoft.com/kb/2554288/&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Columns published from InfoPath fields are recreated when the same InfoPath form template is re-published to more than one document libraries in a SharePoint site&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s also possible to hit problems with InfoPath&amp;#8217;s caching. This tries to be helpful but sometimes can be overzealous or just plain gets confused between different environments. Unfortunately it can result in your testers using the test version of a form in production before the update has been deployed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;too-many-bugs&quot;&gt;Too many bugs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re never gonna know when one&amp;#8217;s going to bite you and cost serious time, again and again and again. There are bugs and unexpected behaviour in the client, when deploying forms with code, and in Forms Services. Pretty embarrassing when you think you have a form &amp;#8220;just right&amp;#8221; and it breaks in front of your demonstration audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-infopath-sales-pitch&quot;&gt;The InfoPath sales pitch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft&amp;#8217;s selling point is that InfoPath is part of Office and any savvy business user can maintain these forms. However this greatly depends on the complexity of the form and the user&amp;#8217;s expertise. Many people struggle as forms get more complicated for the reasons mentioned here (plus more), and introducing multiple environments or custom code makes it nigh impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, InfoPath has its place. Make sure your reasons for using it are the right ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;enough&quot;&gt;Enough!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on! But hopefully this gives you some things to think about before falling into the InfoPath deep end. InfoPath has its place for simpler solutions and usually doesn&amp;#8217;t require a developer resource. Just be careful not to let it cost you dearly later. Fingers crossed that Microsoft will change some fundamental flaws the product has had for a while now in the next version.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/10/do-your-research-before-developing-with-infopath</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/10/do-your-research-before-developing-with-infopath</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-10-31T20:05:19+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Developing for a load balanced SharePoint environment</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are going to deploy to a load balanced environment, a big plus is being able to develop in one. Unfortunately a lot of us don&amp;#8217;t have that luxury! Here are some key points to help out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;managing-state&quot;&gt;Managing state&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always rely on SharePoint&amp;#8217;s central store - the database. Don&amp;#8217;t try and store data on the file system as you will never be sure which server has what copy. Use lists for data that should be exposed to administrators and users. Use SPPersistedObject or the patterns &amp;amp; practices &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff798488.aspx&quot;&gt;Application Setting Manager&lt;/a&gt; for application configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;caching&quot;&gt;Caching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just another method of storing state, albeit one that&amp;#8217;s faster (yet limited in resources)! Be aware when using ASP.NET caching that every server will cache your data separately in its own copy of RAM. These will get out of sync resulting in inconsistencies that you will need to handle. You may find AppFabric Caching as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wictorwilen.se/Post/Improve-performance-of-your-SharePoint-2010-applications-using-Windows-Server-AppFabric-caching.aspx&quot;&gt;described by Wictor Wilén&lt;/a&gt; a good solution to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;thread-safety&quot;&gt;Thread safety&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never store rich objects that aren&amp;#8217;t thread safe such as SPListItem in the cache or any other form of state. Aside from potentially taking up unnecessary space, these objects won&amp;#8217;t work properly once deserialized. Introducing caching also opens up your application to potential threading issues, as explained in &amp;#8220;Understanding the Potential Pitfalls of Thread Synchronization&amp;#8221; &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb687949.aspx&quot;&gt;in this best practices article&lt;/a&gt;. You don&amp;#8217;t need to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.threading.aspx&quot;&gt;System.Threading&lt;/a&gt; to be multithreading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;testing&quot;&gt;Testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you can&amp;#8217;t develop in a load balanced environment, it really pays to test in one. A lot of situations just can&amp;#8217;t be reproduced otherwise! I strongly recommend to ensure your production environment always closely matches test in configuration (even if number of servers is unreasonable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary: always store data in the database to avoid problems with different servers accessing the same content and keep any caching simple and stateless. Oh, and be sure to thoroughly test!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/developing-for-a-load-balanced-sharepoint-environment</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/developing-for-a-load-balanced-sharepoint-environment</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-09-29T21:15:19+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Tailoring SP2010 p&p logging to your application</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexangas.com/blog/?p=289&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, we saw an intro to the logging power found in the SP 2010 patterns &amp;amp; practices library. Now, let&amp;#8217;s make it our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining your own areas and categories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The out-of-the-box behaviour is fine, but it&amp;#8217;s much nicer for both end user and developer to see the actual application name causing the exception, rather than the generic &amp;#8220;Patterns and Practices&amp;#8221;. No problem, you can define your own areas and categories! What does this mean? Examine a ULS log file and you&amp;#8217;ll see at the top a series of column headers. &amp;#8220;Area&amp;#8221; is typically used for the a major piece of functionality or application name. &amp;#8220;Category&amp;#8221; is some component of that functionality. For logging to the Event Viewer, the Source column is used for &amp;#8220;Area&amp;#8221;, and &amp;#8220;Category&amp;#8221; is the first line of the log entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The many ILogger methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before continuing, let&amp;#8217;s examine how we use a custom area and category when calling the ILogger. If you have a look at its interface, you&amp;#8217;ll find several variations of two methods. &lt;strong&gt;LogToOperations&lt;/strong&gt; writes to both the ULS trace log and the Event Viewer. &lt;strong&gt;TraceToDeveloper&lt;/strong&gt; writes to the trace log only. Some variations allow you to specify a category and others don&amp;#8217;t. At this point, you really want to look at the many options and narrow down the list to one or two that are going to be most useful to you. I generally only use the following depending on whether I&amp;#8217;m logging exceptions or information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
void LogToOperations(Exception exception, int eventId, EventSeverity severity, string category);
void LogToOperations(string message, string category);
[/csharp]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the &lt;strong&gt;category&lt;/strong&gt; parameter which is where we set both the area &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; category to use. The supplied string here needs to be of the format &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Area&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;Category&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221;. This is fairly distasteful in design and much like a &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_number_(programming)&quot;&gt;magic number&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;, but that&amp;#8217;s the way the API has been written. I recommend creating a LoggingHelper class that abstracts this away and reduces the risk of making a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Registering the areas and categories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one last trick to perform before using these custom areas and categories. They must be provisioned as part of a farm level feature. This is primarily because updates are made to the SharePoint configuration database which requires execution by an account with farm level permissions. It&amp;#8217;s also because registering new sources for the Event Viewer to use must be done by a user with permissions to write to the Windows registry. Executing this registration as a farm-level event receiver should alleviate these issues (unless you&amp;#8217;re deploying to a locked down environment where you may have some problems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sample code on how to register areas and categories in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff798462.aspx&quot;&gt;SharePoint Guidance documentation&lt;/a&gt;. (There&amp;#8217;s also plenty of other great stuff there about how the logger works and I recommend taking a few minutes to read it.) One extra thing to take note of if you plan on logging to the Event Viewer in a &lt;strong&gt;multi-server farm&lt;/strong&gt; is that this registration needs to take place on each server in the farm. There are &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/chriskeyser/archive/2010/12/20/using-a-sharepoint-timer-job-to-deploy-settings-in-a-farm-for-registering-event-sources.aspx&quot;&gt;instructions on how to do this&lt;/a&gt; by lead SharePoint p&amp;amp;p; developer Chris Keyser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Segue - suggestions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you would have gathered, this library is not perfect. Here&amp;#8217;s some thoughts on gotchas and what I feel could be improved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ILogger interface contains too many method signatures which causes confusion. Most developers will only settle on their chosen one or two. I&amp;#8217;d like to see a simple entity-style class used for specifying logging parameters instead of the many options given.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using a &amp;#8216;magic number&amp;#8217; style string format to select an area and category is error prone. Area and category should be separated, and preferably strongly typed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s clear to see the ILogger interface has been designed around logging to the ULS and Event Log. This makes it not as adaptable to other scenarios. Again, using an entity-style class for parameters would help make it more generic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To register your own custom areas and categories, a farm feature is required so that enough permissions are available to write to the Windows registry. In multi-server farms there is added complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, a lot of these issues only need to be resolved once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the logging functionality provided with the patterns &amp;amp; practices library. It&amp;#8217;s generally easy to use and certainly powerful. There are some issues, but it&amp;#8217;s a great way to get exposure to the benefits of this library and immediately reap rewards!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/tailoring-sp2010-pp-logging-to-your-application</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/tailoring-sp2010-pp-logging-to-your-application</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-09-20T21:02:41+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Intro to SharePoint 2010 patterns & practices - Logging</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Microsoft&amp;#8217;s patterns &amp;amp; practices library for SharePoint 2010 contains plenty of useful information and tools. One of the simplest things you can start using right now is its logging functionality. Check out these handy features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Log to both the ULS trace logs and the Windows Event Viewer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define your own logging categories so they appear under &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; application&amp;#8217;s name everywhere&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support for logging from the sandbox via a provided proxy&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configure log event throttling using the out-of-the-box Diagnostic Logging page in Central Administration&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contextual information such as current URL and logged in user is automatically added to log entries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t worry about logging long messages or correlation IDs, it&amp;#8217;s all handled for you&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the provided logging interface to easily write your own logger&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Service locator provided means almost no code changes when changing to a different logger (for a future blog post)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re a developer that&amp;#8217;s never used the library before, this post helps you dip your toes in the water and harness this logging power!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The p&amp;amp;p release is a little confusing. There&amp;#8217;s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://spg.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;CodePlex project&lt;/a&gt;, which links to various components and where you should ask for help or log any bugs you find. However the code is not kept there - download that from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=64b55569-2168-4545-8b7c-f185b2cf967d&quot;&gt;MS Downloads&lt;/a&gt;. You&amp;#8217;ll want to keep an eye on this page for updates as they aren&amp;#8217;t announced anywhere that I&amp;#8217;ve found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once extracted to your development server, you need to build the library. Everything is open source apart from the service locator (for a later blog post). The solution to build can be found at &lt;code&gt;Source\SharePoint 2010\Microsoft.Practices.SharePoint.sln&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/pandp_solution.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/pandp_solution.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build this project, then copy the output &lt;code&gt;Microsoft.Practices.ServiceLocation.dll&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Microsoft.Practices.SharePoint.Common.dll&lt;/code&gt; to your project and reference them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log away!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the logger is pretty easy. First, add these using statements everywhere you wish to log:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
using Microsoft.Practices.SharePoint.Common.Logging;
using Microsoft.Practices.SharePoint.Common.ServiceLocation;
[/csharp]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then declare the logger as a field and obtain a reference to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
ILogger _logger = SharePointServiceLocator.GetCurrent().GetInstance&lt;ilogger&gt;();
[/csharp]&lt;/ilogger&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;#8217;s log an exception&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
Exception ex = new ApplicationException(&amp;#8220;This is my test exception&amp;#8221;);
_logger.LogToOperations(ex);
[/csharp]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;and see what appears in the ULS log&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;09/08/2010 20:15:34.66 	w3wp.exe (0x15D8)                       	0x0EF0	Patterns and Practices        	SharePoint Guidance           	0000	Information	Category: SharePoint Guidance: An exception has occurred.   ExceptionType: &amp;#8216;ApplicationException&amp;#8217;   ExceptionMessage: &amp;#8216;This is my test exception&amp;#8217;   StackTrace: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;   Source: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;   TargetSite: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;   Additional Information:  Request TimeStamp: &amp;#8216;2010-09-08T20:15:33.2171690+09:30&amp;#8217;  UserName: &amp;#8216;AA\Administrator&amp;#8217;  Request URL: &amp;#8216;http://aasp2010dev:31000/default.aspx?PageView=Shared&amp;amp;InitialTabId;=Ribbon.WebPartPage&amp;amp;VisibilityContext;=WSSWebPartPage&amp;#8217;  User Agent: &amp;#8216;Mozilla/4.0 (compatible; MSIE 7.0; Windows NT 6.1; WOW64; Trident/4.0; SLCC2; .NET CLR 2.0.50727; .NET4.0C; .NET4.0E; InfoPath.3; .NET CLR 3.5.30729; .NET CLR 3.0.30729)&amp;#8217;  Originating IP address: &amp;#8216;127.0.0.1&amp;#8217;	2cc97a55-1c4d-4e22-b145-4de9a3fdf6e1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;and Event Viewer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;`
Log Name:      Application
Source:        Patterns and Practices
Date:          8/09/2010 8:15:34 PM
Event ID:      0
Task Category: None
Level:         Information
Keywords:      Classic
User:          N/A
Computer:      aasp2010dev.aa.com
Description:
Category: SharePoint Guidance: An exception has occurred.
	ExceptionType: &amp;#8216;ApplicationException&amp;#8217;
	ExceptionMessage: &amp;#8216;This is my test exception&amp;#8217;
	StackTrace: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;
	Source: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;
	TargetSite: &amp;#8216;&amp;#8217;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(many other details removed for brevity)&lt;/em&gt;
`&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can see the benefits these simple steps have already given - lots of context relating to exception to help diagnose the problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logging - make it happen!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it for now, but we&amp;#8217;ll be exploring a lot more about this library in the next blog post. Remember - you owe it to yourself and your users to log appropriately. Ease the pain of bugs found in production code!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download and references:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://spg.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;SharePoint Guidance CodePlex Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=64b55569-2168-4545-8b7c-f185b2cf967d&quot;&gt;SharePoint Guidance 2010 Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/intro-to-sharepoint-2010-patterns-practices-logging</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/intro-to-sharepoint-2010-patterns-practices-logging</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-09-14T21:06:49+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Analysis of the Oracle Hyperion Web Part</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post I originally wrote in July 2009 and never got around to properly completing. Because of its age I considered binning it altogether however a quick web search seems to turn up that nothing has changed for this humble web part. This is more of a rant about vendors that can&amp;#8217;t be bothered to integrate their products with SharePoint using best practices. The person that ends up suffering is &amp;#8220;the SharePoint guy/gal&amp;#8221; who is lumped with deploying this rubbish. Hopefully it helps someone else out there that&amp;#8217;s stuck in the same boat I once was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rewind-to-july-2009&quot;&gt;Rewind to July 2009&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently given the task of deploying the Oracle Hyperion web part for testing in one of our SharePoint sites. There was no formal requirement for this, it was simply requested because there appears to be no documentation or information available on what functionality this mysterious web part can provide. What better way to find out than to deploy it for testing, right? There are even quite &lt;a href=&quot;http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E12825_01/epm.111/pit_setup.pdf&quot;&gt;detailed instructions&lt;/a&gt; available!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well stop right there, folks. In fact before you read any further, my recommendation is to run far, far away from this unusual piece of technology. Why? Well let&amp;#8217;s start with the high-level changes you&amp;#8217;ll need to make to your SharePoint environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the web part itself&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configure single sign-on (SSO) - makes sense as Oracle is an external product&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a &amp;#8216;proxy page&amp;#8217; - a virtual IIS application inside your SharePoint application&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install a custom HTTP handler&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a custom database&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm&amp;#8230; seems rather unusual so far (particularly that custom database - don&amp;#8217;t we already have data stores in both SharePoint &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; Oracle?). But then read the fine print as it describes three best practice no-nos all on one page (that&amp;#8217;s page 71 if you&amp;#8217;re following along readers) without even so much as to explain what effect the changes will have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set the trust level to Full.&lt;/strong&gt;
Say goodbye to security in your SharePoint farm right here. With trust level set to Full, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.tylerholmes.com/2008/10/don-set-your-sharepoint-app-to-full.html&quot;&gt;custom code can run without restriction&lt;/a&gt; and do whatever it likes. &lt;strong&gt;Really Bad Idea.&lt;/strong&gt; Oracle, please look into Code Access Security.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replace the default SQL Server session state provider for SharePoint.&lt;/strong&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ll be honest. I have no idea what they are doing here or why. All I know is that the chances of support from Microsoft on such a fundamental change to how session state works in SharePoint has to be zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment out the PublishingHttpModule.&lt;/strong&gt;
Say goodbye to one of the best features in SharePoint - publishing pages. For yet another strange and unexplained reason, this has to go. Not sure if they put it back somewhere with their custom code, this isn&amp;#8217;t mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now follow through almost twenty pages, some with screenshots, to configure this nightmare, and that doesn&amp;#8217;t included setting up SSO. I like to think I&amp;#8217;m pretty good at puzzling out this sort of thing, but this baby has got me beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I found that might help others&amp;#8230; Add the server hosting SharePoint to the Local Intranet zone in Internet Explorer security settings. Otherwise, you might encounter an &amp;#8220;Invalid index&amp;#8221; message while browsing the repository in Internet Explorer. Also, uninstall the Enhanced Security Configuration from Windows Server to prevent logon issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if anyone, anywhere has been able to successfully deploy this thing? More to the point, why did Oracle bother to even develop it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/analysis-of-the-oracle-hyperion-web-part</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/09/analysis-of-the-oracle-hyperion-web-part</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-09-13T13:10:56+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Why it's an exciting time to be part of SharePoint Overflow!</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sharepointoverflow.com&quot;&gt;SharePoint Overflow&lt;/a&gt; started as one of the first &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stackexchange.com&quot;&gt;Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt; sites (running version 1.0). It&amp;#8217;s also been one of the most successful. We&amp;#8217;ve been able to attract some fantastic contributors including several MVPs and our traffic stats have continuously increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the discontinuation of the original Stack Exchange business model &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.stackoverflow.com/2010/04/changes-to-stack-exchange/&quot;&gt;was announced&lt;/a&gt;, I felt plunged into the wilderness and lost motivation in the site for a little while. Suddenly, calling this community our own while running it on the awesome platform that powered sites such as Stack Overflow appeared impossible come April 13 2011. Stack Exchange 2.0 would be owned by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; team with input from the community (instead of owned by members of the community) and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.osqa.net/&quot;&gt;closest alternative platform&lt;/a&gt; was (and still is) a long way behind in functionality and general awesomeness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the interests of the fantastic community and content I wanted to see continue, I got over myself! I arranged with &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/nickswan&quot;&gt;Nick Swan&lt;/a&gt;, the original SharePoint Overflow mastermind that we look at moving the platform to Stack Exchange 2.0. After eventually being able to contact the very busy Stack Exchange team, things were put into motion and &lt;a href=&quot;http://area51.stackexchange.com/proposals/28921/sharepoint-overflow?referrer=UhOiV0ReN8IdOf0kzJX7fA2&quot;&gt;here we are&lt;/a&gt; (87% committed at time of writing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what&amp;#8217;s going to make SharePoint Overflow 2.0 so exciting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our site started using a copy of how Stack Overflow functioned back in mid-late 2009. Now, if you&amp;#8217;ve ever read &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.stackexchange.com/&quot;&gt;the Stack Exchange team blog&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;#8217;ll know they&amp;#8217;ve added many new features since then. Some of these will be great for us! Here are my picks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll be exposed to a greater audience&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Exchange sites are promoted across the network. You can see this in ads for questions on other sites, Twitter feeds, the listings of &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackexchange.com/sites&quot;&gt;Stack Exchange sites&lt;/a&gt;, they&amp;#8217;re everywhere! One of the great things is that a single login to the Stack Exchange network associates accounts across sites. This boils down to it being easy for people to come and join us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We _could&lt;/em&gt; be the keepers of all existing SharePoint questions from the trilogy sites_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a community in association with Stack Exchange, we may decide that SharePoint Overflow is where all SharePoint questions should live. That means many questions from across the trilogy sites will be migrated, as well as any new questions. It also gives those questions about SharePoint that don&amp;#8217;t seem to quite &amp;#8220;fit&amp;#8221; in one of the existing trilogy sites a home (great &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.pentalogic.net/2011/03/your-sharepoint-community-needs-you/&quot;&gt;explanation by Stuart Pegg&lt;/a&gt;). This should make us the largest SharePoint community Q&amp;amp;A; site outside of MSDN and TechNet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: &amp;#8220;trilogy&amp;#8221; here means the sites &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; (programming), &lt;a href=&quot;http://serverfault.com&quot;&gt;Server Fault&lt;/a&gt; (systems administration), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://superuser.com&quot;&gt;Super User&lt;/a&gt; (computer enthusiasts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll have more encouragement to accept answers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that&amp;#8217;s always been a problem in our site has been encouraging people to accept answers (and vote generally). Complete speculation from me is that this isn&amp;#8217;t a nice experience or have any obvious benefits on MSDN/TechNet, which is the platform most of our users are previously familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reason aside, users will have an &amp;#8220;accept rate&amp;#8221; shown underneath their reputation on questions they ask, just like on &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/q/214714/6651&quot;&gt;my Stack Overflow question here&lt;/a&gt;. This feature made a big difference when it was introduced on the trilogy sites! Sadly we just missed out on it with Stack Exchange 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll have our own meta site to discuss how the site should be run&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve really felt a bit in the dark with how to administer the site, and haven&amp;#8217;t wanted to clutter it up with a lot of meta questions. (We used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sharepointoverflow.com/questions/tagged/sharepoint-overflow&quot;&gt;sharepoint-overflow&lt;/a&gt; tag for this.) With our own meta site (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meta.wordpress.stackexchange.com&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;), it will be much easier for us all to discuss the future and do the best thing in the interests of our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll have several interesting possibilities of support&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stack Exchange team really actually care about supporting communities and making the Internet a better place. For example, they&amp;#8217;ve recently announced &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.stackoverflow.com/2011/02/community-conference-sponsorships/&quot;&gt;community conference sponsorships&lt;/a&gt; to help people share knowledge and experiences. If they can do that, I think we might at least be able to get some stickers?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The future is bright&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#8217;s my feelings on the exciting future of our site! These are exciting times, so please, &lt;a href=&quot;http://area51.stackexchange.com/proposals/28921/sharepoint-overflow?referrer=UhOiV0ReN8IdOf0kzJX7fA2&quot;&gt;come and join us&lt;/a&gt;! Here&amp;#8217;s how to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sharepointoverflow.com/questions/9270/how-can-i-help-sharepoint-overflow-move-to-stack-exchange-2-0-definition-phase&quot;&gt;spread the word&lt;/a&gt;. (As &lt;a href=&quot;http://tomresing.com/blog/Lists/Posts/Post.aspx?ID=27&quot;&gt;explained by Tom Resing&lt;/a&gt; we most need committers to have at least 200 reputation on other Stack Exchange sites.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a very sincere &lt;strong&gt;thank you&lt;/strong&gt; to the fantastic members of the community that have helped us become so successful (notably moderators &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/sympmarc&quot;&gt;Marc Anderson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/charlesdlee&quot;&gt;Charlie Lee&lt;/a&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/03/why-its-an-exciting-time-to-be-part-of-sharepoint-overflow</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2011/03/why-its-an-exciting-time-to-be-part-of-sharepoint-overflow</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-03-11T19:00:13+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Administrators! Stop before deploying that custom code!</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Even with no development knowledge, there&amp;#8217;s a simple and quick tool that SharePoint administrators can run before deploying a solution package or web part to get some idea on whether it could cause instability your farm! It&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.msdn.microsoft.com/SPDisposeCheck&quot;&gt;SPDisposeCheck&lt;/a&gt; and is particularly useful to keep an eye on the work done by a third party or even internally, with no developer knowledge whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool was released by Microsoft in early 2009 to help developers check for memory leaks in their code. However there&amp;#8217;s no reason why an administrator can&amp;#8217;t do the same. Memory leaks can cause &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa973248.aspx&quot;&gt;performance problems and general instability&lt;/a&gt; in your SharePoint farm. This tool tells you of any potential problems, and here&amp;#8217;s how to use it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;http://download.microsoft.com/download/B/4/D/B4D279A0-E159-40BF-A5E8-F49ABDBE95C7/SPDisposeCheck.msi&quot;&gt;SPDisposeCheck&lt;/a&gt; and install. By default this will copy SPDisposeCheck.exe to &lt;code&gt;C:\Program Files\Microsoft\SharePoint Dispose Check&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Examine the deployment file you have been given. If this is a WSP file, rename its extension to CAB and extract all DLL files. SPDisposeCheck also works on EXE files if you&amp;#8217;ve been asked to run a console application.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each DLL or EXE, run SPDisposeCheck using the filename as a parameter. To be assured of no SharePoint memory leaks, check that the &amp;#8220;Total Found&amp;#8221; line is 0.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s an example that shows a potential leak:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/SPDisposeCheckOutput.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/SPDisposeCheckOutput-300x253.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPDisposeCheckOutput&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the tool finds some issues then you should query this with the developers. However as the tool itself states, this doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily mean there is a leak! Unfortunately it can report false positives depending on how the code has been written. Regardless, make sure you have an assurance that the tool is run as part of their release process and any flagged issues have been checked. The tool will never miss a problem with a false negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s as simple as that. Be sure to add SPDisposeCheck to your admin toolkit and don&amp;#8217;t let those developers get away with dodgy code!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/11/administrators-stop-before-deploying-that-custom-code</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/11/administrators-stop-before-deploying-that-custom-code</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-11-06T18:53:56+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Query Demo Web Part</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1374137/how-to-query-data-in-sharepoint-from-multiple-lists/&quot;&gt;question recently came up on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; about querying data from multiple SharePoint lists and binding the results to a GridView control. I realised there were some types of SharePoint queries I hadn&amp;#8217;t explored, and that it would be interesting to compare them and see how they work in a web part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1374137/how-to-query-data-in-sharepoint-from-multiple-lists/1444416#1444416&quot;&gt;I created the SPQueryDemo web part!&lt;/a&gt; It tests and displays results from the following types of queries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For loop&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GetListItems from Lists web service&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SPQuery for SPList objects&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SPSiteDataQuery for cross-site list queries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CrossListQueryInfo for cached cross-site list queries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PortalSiteMapProvider for SharePoint Server publishing sites only&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://spquerydemo.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;Download it from CodePlex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve also used this project to try out using user controls for output rather than the traditional dynamic creation of controls in a SharePoint web part. This has been attempted with an MVP-style pattern which I&amp;#8217;d really appreciate any feedback on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future I&amp;#8217;d like to &lt;a href=&quot;http://spquerydemo.codeplex.com/WorkItem/List.aspx&quot;&gt;add more functionality&lt;/a&gt;, particularly for different query options and types of queries. There is also an annoying bug when changing the query type where the page needs to be refreshed before changes take affect. If anyone would like to help or just check out the code, please &lt;a href=&quot;http://spquerydemo.codeplex.com/SourceControl/ListDownloadableCommits.aspx&quot;&gt;download the source&lt;/a&gt; and hack away! You can also contact me via this blog post or &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/alexangas&quot;&gt;via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/09/query-demo-web-part</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/09/query-demo-web-part</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-09-29T22:36:53+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>When alerts don't work 'by design'</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve just spent many fruitless hours trying to find a bug in my code that has been causing minor but visible pain for a number of users - and it was never even there. You would think after spending several years working with SharePoint I would know all of the ins-and-outs of alerts but not this one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&amp;#8220;Require Check Out&amp;#8221; is set to Yes (toggle the screenshot below in your mind, please!)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/requireco.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/requireco.png&quot; alt=&quot;Require Check Out&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alert created to only send when new items are added  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/alertnew.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/alertnew.png&quot; alt=&quot;Send alerts when new items are added&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User does not receive alerts on new items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;#8217;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &amp;#8220;Require Check Out&amp;#8221; is enabled, alerts for a new document are only processed when it is checked in, and &lt;em&gt;only the most recent alert event is kept&lt;/em&gt;. Here&amp;#8217;s a simplified version of what SharePoint is doing behind the scenes when a user sets an alert for new items only:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action
Alert-related behaviour
Response to user&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User uploads a document&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;New item&amp;#8221; event registered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Fill in properties and check in&amp;#8221; page displays&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User clicks &amp;#8220;Check In&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Changed item&amp;#8221; event registered and alert functionality triggered - most recent event is processed, sending a &amp;#8220;Changed item&amp;#8221; alert (&amp;#8220;New item&amp;#8221; event is discarded)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Document checked in and user receives no alert&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also an issue for users opting to receive alerts with the &amp;#8220;All changes&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Existing items are modified&amp;#8221; options set. Their alerts will read the item has changed when actually it is new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked about this on the SharePoint forums and received a good &lt;a href=&quot;http://social.technet.microsoft.com/Forums/en-US/sharepointgeneral/thread/948a168d-22f3-4a09-92d7-2e6558b0f0fb&quot;&gt;response from Lu Zou-MSFT&lt;/a&gt; confirming this behaviour. Unfortunately it&amp;#8217;s unknown if this behaviour will change for SharePoint 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/08/when-alerts-dont-work-by-design</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/08/when-alerts-dont-work-by-design</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-08-24T19:20:18+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Showing the bulleted links list view</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;A user recently took quite a shine to this lovely bulleted view of links in the list view web part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/usefullinks.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/usefullinks.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bulleted link list view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wanted all of their existing links list to be changed over to use this view. What makes this case more unusual is that this is actually the view displayed as &amp;#8220;&amp;lt;Summary view&amp;gt;&amp;#8221; in the web UI:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/usefultp.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/08/usefultp.png&quot; alt=&quot;Links toolpart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much fighting with the SPViewCollection on the list, I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;http://ketulpatel.wordpress.com/2008/06/25/programatically-working-with-listviewwebpart-using-non-default-view/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on Ketul Patel&amp;#8217;s blog. He showed that to get a reference to this &amp;#8216;hidden&amp;#8217; view, it is necessary to use the mouthy method &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.sharepoint.splist.getuncustomizedviewbybaseviewid.aspx&quot;&gt;SPList.GetUncustomizedViewFromBaseViewId()&lt;/a&gt;. The list view web part can then be changed to use the markup for the summary view. (Note that the web part needs to be re-added to the page so that the changes take effect correctly.) Here is a method that does this all this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
public static ListViewWebPart ReplaceWithBaseView(
	ListViewWebPart listViewWebPart, SPList list,
	int baseViewId, SPLimitedWebPartManager limitedWebPartManager)
{
	string zoneID = listViewWebPart.ZoneID;
	int zoneIndex = listViewWebPart.ZoneIndex;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;SPView view = list.GetUncustomizedViewByBaseViewId(baseViewId);

ListViewWebPart replacementWebPart = new ListViewWebPart
{
	Title = listViewWebPart.Title,
	ListName = listViewWebPart.ListName,
	Hidden = false,
	FilterString = listViewWebPart.FilterString,
	SuppressWebPartChrome = listViewWebPart.SuppressWebPartChrome,
	ViewContentTypeId = listViewWebPart.ViewContentTypeId,
	ListViewXml = view.HtmlSchemaXml,
	ExportMode = listViewWebPart.ExportMode
};

limitedWebPartManager.DeleteWebPart(listViewWebPart);
limitedWebPartManager.AddWebPart(replacementWebPart, zoneID, zoneIndex);

return replacementWebPart; } [/csharp]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to call the above method, it&amp;#8217;s simply a matter of getting a reference to the web part page and the web part. The magic number for &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;&amp;lt;Summary view&amp;gt;&amp;#8221; is 0&lt;/strong&gt;. Here is the calling code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[csharp]
SPList usefulLinksList = web.Lists[&amp;#8220;Useful Links&amp;#8221;];
using (SPLimitedWebPartManager webPartManager =
		web.GetLimitedWebPartManager(&amp;#8220;default.aspx&amp;#8221;, PersonalizationScope.Shared))
{
	try
	{
		foreach (WebPart webPart in webPartManager.WebParts)
		{
			if (webPart.Title == &amp;#8220;Useful Links&amp;#8221;)
			{
				ListViewWebPart listViewWebPart = (ListViewWebPart)webPart;
				ReplaceWithBaseView(listViewWebPart, usefulLinksList, 0, webPartManager);
				break;
			}
		}
	}
	finally
	{
		webPartManager.Web.Dispose();
	}
}
[/csharp]&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/08/showing-the-bulleted-links-list-view</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/08/showing-the-bulleted-links-list-view</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-08-05T18:45:02+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Explorer View breaks after IE8 install on Windows 2003</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Since installing Internet Explorer 8 on my Windows Server 2003 development machine I&amp;#8217;ve been unable to use Explorer View, with the error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please wait while Explorer View is loaded. If Explorer View does not appear, your browser may not support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching around, the main reasons seem to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SharePoint site behind SSL - no fix at time of writing&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IE security level changes - fixable by adjusting security levels or adding SharePoint site to Trusted Sites zone&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WebClient service not running - fixable by starting this Windows service and ensure it is set to start automatically&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the problem was #3, however attempts to start WebClient resulted in &amp;#8220;File not found&amp;#8221;-type errors. The following error was logged in the Event Viewer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The application-specific permission settings do not grant Local Activation permission for the COM Server application with CLSID
{BA126AD1-2166-11D1-B1D0-00805FC1270E}
to the user NT AUTHORITY\NETWORK SERVICE SID (S-1-5-20).  This security permission can be modified using the Component Services administrative tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This familiar problem usually occursin SharePoint installations with the &lt;strong&gt;IIS WAMREG admin Service&lt;/strong&gt; in Component Services. However this time searching the registry for the GUID in the error I had came up with the &amp;#8220;Network Connection Manager Class&amp;#8221;. Then searching for the GUID in its AppID key of {27AF75ED-20D9-11D1-B1CE-00805FC1270E} resulted in the **netman **component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then configured the security as described by the error in Component Services:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/nslp.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/nslp-248x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;netman Launch Permission&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After stopping and restarting MS DTC I was able to start WebClient successfully and Explorer View worked again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/explorer-view-breaks-after-ie8-install-on-windows-2003</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/explorer-view-breaks-after-ie8-install-on-windows-2003</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-07-31T07:35:11+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Debugging file locking in the GAC</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever find that your solution files have been &amp;#8220;successfully deployed&amp;#8221; according to SharePoint, yet the updated code isn&amp;#8217;t taking effect? Perhaps you are trying to debug but breakpoints aren&amp;#8217;t being hit when normally there&amp;#8217;s no problem. Yet for some reason rebooting the server fixes the problem&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that&amp;#8217;s the case, the reason is probably &lt;strong&gt;file locking&lt;/strong&gt;, most likely to occur if you have assemblies that need to be deployed to the Global Assembly Cache (GAC). If you ever find yourself in this situation, download a copy of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb896653.aspx&quot;&gt;Process Explorer&lt;/a&gt; tool, and follow these steps to verify:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb896653.aspx&quot;&gt;Process Explorer&lt;/a&gt; on the server affected.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Press Ctrl+F, or in the menu click &lt;strong&gt;Find&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Find Handle or DLL&amp;#8230;&lt;/strong&gt;, or just click the binoculars icon on the toolbar:&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/petoolbar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Process Explorer toolbar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type the name of the assembly DLL and click &lt;strong&gt;Search&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the Handle or DLL column, look for any assemblies located in the path &lt;strong&gt;C:\WINDOWS\assembly\temp&lt;/strong&gt;. These lines tell you what process is locking the assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;#8221;attachment_181&amp;#8221; align=&amp;#8221;aligncenter&amp;#8221; width=&amp;#8221;638&amp;#8221; caption=&amp;#8221;OWSTIMER.EXE is the culprit!&amp;#8221;]&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/peasmlist.png&quot; alt=&quot;OWSTIMER.EXE is the culprit&quot; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;C:\WINDOWS\assembly\temp&lt;/strong&gt; folder is Windows&amp;#8217; equivalent of &amp;#8220;assembly purgatory&amp;#8221; where the assembly will sit until Windows can deploy it. If the currently deployed assembly cannot be overwritten as it is already locked by a process then the DLL will stay there until the process releases the lock or ends, or until Windows is restarted (also ending the process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One example where this problem can occur is when a WSP solution containing custom e-mail event receivers is upgraded. The timer service, OWSTIMER.EXE, executes event receivers via the &lt;strong&gt;Windows SharePoint Services Incoming E-Mail&lt;/strong&gt; job. As the OWSTIMER.EXE process isn&amp;#8217;t restarted when a solution is deployed, it will always hold onto the lock for the DLL containing the event receivers. The solution is to restart the &lt;strong&gt;Windows SharePoint Services Timer&lt;/strong&gt; service on each web front end server. If you&amp;#8217;re finding this problem in development, &lt;a href=&quot;http://wspbuilder.codeplex.com&quot;&gt;WSPBuilder&lt;/a&gt; v1.06 adds a &amp;#8220;Recycle the Windows SharePoint Services Timer&amp;#8221; option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem can also occur when using Visual Studio if certain combinations of add-ins are installed. You can again check this by using Process Explorer and verify if DEVENV.EXE is the locking process. If so, take a good look at the add-ins you actually need. Regularly restarting Visual Studio is very frustrating and will severely cut your productivity!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/debugging-file-locking-in-the-gac</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/debugging-file-locking-in-the-gac</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-07-29T21:25:23+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Gotchas configuring SSO</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;SharePoint 2007 seems to have some real weirdness going on with configuring SSO. I&amp;#8217;ve been setting it up in a test environment in a very simple way, using the farm administrator account for everything: Microsoft Single Sign-on Service account, Single Sign-On Administrator Account, Enterprise Application Definition Administrator Account, etc&amp;#8230; Note that &lt;em&gt;this is for testing only and is not best practice&lt;/em&gt;! Here are the problems I&amp;#8217;ve found&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weirdness #1:&lt;/strong&gt; Error 0x80630005. Verify this account has sufficient permissions and try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution:&lt;/strong&gt; Log in to the server as the &amp;#8220;Microsoft Single Sign-on Service&amp;#8221; service account. As described by &lt;a href=&quot;http://cs.grossmann.com/blogs/fg/archive/2007/09/02/setting-up-single-sign-on-in-sharepoint-2007-errors.aspx&quot;&gt;Frank Grossmann&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weirdness #2:&lt;/strong&gt; Error 0x8063064a. Verify this account has sufficient permissions and try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution:&lt;/strong&gt; Remote desktop to the server&amp;#8217;s console (i.e. use &lt;strong&gt;mstsc /console&lt;/strong&gt;) or physically log in to the server. As described by &lt;a href=&quot;http://msmvps.com/blogs/OBTS/archive/2005/08/20/63535.aspx&quot;&gt;Dave Sobel&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc262932.aspx&quot;&gt;Microsoft documentation for configuring SSO&lt;/a&gt; implies this but is not explicit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note that you must be logged into the SharePoint Central Administration Web site on a farm server to configure single sign-on (SSO) for Office SharePoint Server 2007. If you attempt to configure SSO on a workstation or any computer that is not a farm server, you will see an error message that reads &amp;#8220;Single sign-on cannot be configured from this server. To configure single sign-on, go to the computer running the single sign-on service and specify these settings locally.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t finished the configuration yet but hopefully there won&amp;#8217;t be more problems. The best guide I&amp;#8217;ve found is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thorprojects.com/blog/archive/2008/08/02/moss-single-sign-on-setup-step-by-step.aspx&quot;&gt;MOSS Single Sign On Setup Step-By-Step&lt;/a&gt; and beats what Microsoft provides.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/gotchas-configuring-sso</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/gotchas-configuring-sso</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-07-28T15:13:05+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>"The rows you modified could not be saved to the server due to validation errors"</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Encountered a strange problem copying and pasting between the datasheet views of two contact lists. Only the Contact and Country fields were showing in the datasheet view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing the paste, the following error appeared:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;#8221;attachment_159&amp;#8221; align=&amp;#8221;aligncenter&amp;#8221; width=&amp;#8221;690&amp;#8221; caption=&amp;#8221;The rows you modified could not be saved to the server due to validation errors. This is usually caused by invalid default values.&amp;#8221;]&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/invalid1.png&quot; alt=&quot;invalid1&quot; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The error gives some clue as to the problem. I then attempted to add a single entry manually (without the paste) and received a new error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;#8221;attachment_160&amp;#8221; align=&amp;#8221;aligncenter&amp;#8221; width=&amp;#8221;786&amp;#8221; caption=&amp;#8221;Columns that require data are not included in this view. If you want to edit rows that are missing data in these columns, or add new rows, you must first add the required columns to the view.&amp;#8221;]&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/invalid2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Columns that require data are not included in this view. If you want to edit rows that are missing data in these columns, or add new rows, you must first add the required columns to the view.&quot; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I added all of the columns to the view and at last found the column causing the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;#8221;attachment_161&amp;#8221; align=&amp;#8221;aligncenter&amp;#8221; width=&amp;#8221;288&amp;#8221; caption=&amp;#8221;You must specify a non-blank value for Title.&amp;#8221;]&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/invalid3.png&quot; alt=&quot;You must specify a non-blank value for Title.&quot; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting the Title field to not be required fixed the issue!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/the-rows-you-modified-could-not-be-saved-to-the-server-due-to-validation-errors</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/07/the-rows-you-modified-could-not-be-saved-to-the-server-due-to-validation-errors</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-07-21T17:05:22+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Populate a SharePoint site collection from Excel</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve needed to populate a site collection with many hundreds of sites in an automated fashion several times over the last couple of years. Every time the business owner gives me an Excel spreadsheet of the sites they want created. So rather than reinvent the wheel - again! - I&amp;#8217;ve decided to start developing something reasonably generic and release it to my very first Codeplex project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first version is designed for a topology where each segment of the URL has its siblings in common. For example, &lt;strong&gt;Industry &amp;gt; Brand &amp;gt; Product&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Division &amp;gt; Sector &amp;gt; Department&lt;/strong&gt;. Depending on feedback I might make this more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of feedback, I&amp;#8217;d really appreciate any comments from end users or other developers on desired features or comments on code WTFs! Please go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://spexcelator.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;SPExcelator on Codeplex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, download and add to the discussion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, special thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/robinmeure/status/2190226258&quot;&gt;Robin Meuré&lt;/a&gt; for suggesting use of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://exceldatareader.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;Excel Data Reader&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/06/populate-a-sharepoint-site-collection-from-excel</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2009/06/populate-a-sharepoint-site-collection-from-excel</guid>
                <pubDate>2009-06-20T16:01:29+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Workspace permissions - Part 3: "Workarounds and The Future"</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A crucial foundation of SharePoint is its powerful permissioning model. This is a series of three posts that discusses SharePoint permission assignment in a Project Server project workspace. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/25/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; explained how permissions are assigned and problems with the feature’s design. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/26/workspace-permissions-part-2-access-denied/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; discusses a particular bug (i.e. the feature’s implementation). Finally, Part 3 has some solutions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve looked at the problems with this feature, so what can we do about it? Well the new Project Server 2007 eventing model isn&amp;#8217;t broken, so if you have a developer handy use that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, uncheck the Workspace Permissions box in Server Settings / Project Workspace Provisioning Settings. Then, have a look at the WssInterop event WssWorkspaceCreated. This fires whenever, um, a workspace is created. The initial state of a created workspace is with permission inheritance broken and the service account assigned to the workspace with Full Control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, use &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.sharepoint.spweb.ensureuser.aspx&quot;&gt;SPWeb.EnsureUser&lt;/a&gt; for each user you&amp;#8217;d like to give access to the workspace. This works by adding the user to the SPWeb if they haven&amp;#8217;t been already. This does not give the added users any permissions to the workspace. SPWeb.EnsureUser also works with Active Directory groups, so a model where every user needs read access can be simply accomplished. Finally, use &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.sharepoint.spweb.roleassignments.aspx&quot;&gt;SPWeb.RoleAssignments&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.sharepoint.spweb.roledefinitions.aspx&quot;&gt;SPWeb.RoleDefinitions&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/microsoft.sharepoint.sproleassignment.roledefinitionbindings.aspx&quot;&gt;SPRoleAssignment.RoleDefinitionBindings&lt;/a&gt; to assign users the correct permissions (sorry, hopelessly glossed over but there are examples out there on how to use these).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something else to note about a custom solution is that despite unchecking the Workspace Permissions box earlier on, Project Server&amp;#8217;s behaviour does not change when giving access to the PWA site. It will still handle this for you according to the rules in &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/25/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, leaving you to configure the permissions for the workspace with custom code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works fine and if you are able to make use of Active Directory groups, is fast as well. Plus now that you&amp;#8217;ve gone custom, you have all of the freedom (and traps) of flexibility and the ability to create your own permission assignment rules. Don&amp;#8217;t forget you&amp;#8217;ll need to invest time in creating custom administration pages to manage those as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about going forward and sticking with the product for a solution? For Project Server 14 or 2009 or 2010 I have no idea if there will be any changes to the workspace permissions functionality. If you agree that this feature needs looking at, please give feedback to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/project/&quot;&gt;Project Server team&lt;/a&gt; as they do read it and listen (I&amp;#8217;ve had great responses from &lt;a href=&quot;http://evildoctorporkchop.spaces.live.com/&quot;&gt;Treb Gatte&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/brismith/&quot;&gt;Brian Smith&lt;/a&gt; on other issues). Hopefully bugs will be fixed and the feature improved next release!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and I hope this helps someone else out there with similar experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-3-workarounds-and-the-future</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-3-workarounds-and-the-future</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-11-27T08:00:26+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Workspace permissions - Part 2: "Access Denied"</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;_A crucial foundation of SharePoint is its powerful permissioning model. This is a series of three posts that discusses SharePoint permission assignment in a Project Server project workspace. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/25/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; explained how permissions are assigned and problems with the feature’s design. Part 2 discusses a particular bug (i.e. the feature’s implementation). Finally, Part 3 has some solutions.
_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve been having some great successes out of your Project Server solution you&amp;#8217;ll probably be building up quite a few users and workspaces. One particular customer I&amp;#8217;m aware of has over 1000 of each. To try and get around the inflexible rules outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/25/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, they&amp;#8217;ve decided to give every user at least read access to every workspace. Unfortunately this has uncovered a particularly nasty SQL deadlock bug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;10/06/2008 15:33:59.86 Microsoft.Office.Project.Server (0x1540)   0x12C4 Windows SharePoint Services     Database                                  6f8g      Unexpected       Unexpected query execution failure, error code 1205. Additional error information from SQL Server is included below. &quot;Transaction (Process ID 151) was deadlocked on lock resources with another process and has been chosen as the deadlock victim. Rerun the transaction.&quot; Query text (if available): &quot;{?=call proc_SecAddPrincipalToRole(?,?,?,?,?,?)}&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bug happens when one or more of the following operations is occurring at a time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creating a new workspace by publishing a project (queue job &amp;#8220;WSS Workspace Create&amp;#8221;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resynchronising workspace permissions from Server Settings / Project Workspaces (queue job &amp;#8220;WSS Workspace Membership Synchronisation&amp;#8221;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changing a user&amp;#8217;s Project Server groups which results in changes to SharePoint permissions (queue job &amp;#8220;User Synchronization for Project Web Access App Root Site and Project WSS Workspaces&amp;#8221;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bug hits, permissions are only partially assigned so as this happens again and again, a user&amp;#8217;s consistency of access disappears. The only solution is to try and resynchronise the workspace with fingers crossed that it succeeds without another SQL deadlock. But you&amp;#8217;re completely out of luck when running a batch job that affects several workspaces such as number 3 above. The workspace it reached before everything went horribly wrong doesn&amp;#8217;t appear to be logged!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the SQL deadlock failures, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/websvcwssinterop.wssinterop.synchronizemembershipforpwaapprootsite.aspx&quot;&gt;SynchronizeMembershipForPwaAppRootSite()&lt;/a&gt; method in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/websvcwssinterop.wssinterop_methods.aspx&quot;&gt;WssInterop&lt;/a&gt; web service has been looked at. This performs a complete resynchronisation across all workspaces, functionality that is not available through the UI. Unfortunately with testing in UAT (less powerful than production but still a three server farm), this operation was going to run for days. Also, no other sync jobs could occur at the same time or else it would be SQL deadlock again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs are the worst, but implementation is also a shocker because of the huge length of time these jobs take to run. For example, up to 7 minutes for numbers 1 or 2 above, and 15-45 minutes for number 3 depending on number of users with changed permissions. This is exacerbated as more workspaces are created (the problem seems to be more related to number of workspaces rather than number of users). The server environment where this issue is occurring is very powerful and speed should not be an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve seen from &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.wordpress.com/2008/11/25/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; the deficiencies in design of this feature, but now also it&amp;#8217;s implementation. So things can only get better in Part 3, coming next!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-2-access-denied</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-2-access-denied</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-11-26T08:00:48+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Workspace permissions - Part 1: "By Design"</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A crucial foundation of SharePoint is its powerful permissioning model. This is a series of three posts that discusses SharePoint permission assignment in a Project Server project workspace. Part 1 explains how permissions are assigned and problems with the feature&amp;#8217;s design. Part 2 discusses a particular bug (i.e. the feature&amp;#8217;s implementation). Finally, Part 3 has some solutions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Server has its own SharePoint security groups which almost precisely equate to the standard SharePoint groups of Read, Contribute, Design and Full Control. The TechNet article &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc197668.aspx&quot;&gt;Coordinate Project Server and Windows SharePoint Services security&lt;/a&gt; is the official word for exactly how permissions are assigned. Essentially just as SharePoint has its own built-in list of groups for &amp;#8220;Read&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Contribute&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Design&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Full Control&amp;#8221;, then Project Server comes to the party with &amp;#8220;Readers (Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Team members (Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Project Managers (Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Web Administrators (Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221;&amp;#8230; blurrgh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a simplified summary of the rules that explain how users get their permissions. This is without the &amp;#8220;(Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221; suffix but with standard SharePoint group names in brackets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User that publishes the project has Project Manager (Design) permissions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users assigned to tasks within the project have Team Member (Contribute) permissions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users on the Resource Sheet of a project have Reader (Read) permissions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users that have Manage Windows SharePoint Services permission have Web Administrator (Full Control) permission over all workspaces&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users that have Save Project permission have Project Manager (Design) permission over all workspaces&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks complicated and it is. Try explaining to a project manager that access to documents in their workspace depends on who is added to the project&amp;#8217;s Resource Sheet. It just doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense! Then try explaining to an administrator why there is a group called &amp;#8220;Readers (Microsoft Office Project Server)&amp;#8221; as well as the standard SharePoint group called &amp;#8220;Read&amp;#8221;. It just doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;#8217;s the inflexibility of the rules themselves. There are no options - they are either on or off. And if you don&amp;#8217;t go with MS on this one folks and uncheck the box for Workspace Permissions in Server Settings / Project Workspace Provisioning Settings, then only the Project Server service account is given access to new workspaces! This is hardly useful to the humble user needing to assign permissions who will never get their hands on &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; particular username and password. It just doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t worry, there are solutions. However, they don&amp;#8217;t come until Part 3! Next we look at how Microsoft&amp;#8217;s solution is also slow, and even worse, buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/11/workspace-permissions-part-1-by-design</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-11-25T08:00:37+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Programmatically retrieving the name of an SSP</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/58809/retrieving-the-associated-shared-service-providers-name&quot;&gt;was asked&lt;/a&gt; on the new Stack Overflow programming questions site recently (which you should really check out and start using if you don&amp;#8217;t already!). Getting the SSP name is something that I&amp;#8217;ve needed to do to build the SSP URL for &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa974413.aspx&quot;&gt;impersonating access to the Project Server PSI&lt;/a&gt;. I used to think that the URL had to live in a config file. Then after some digging into Project Server&amp;#8217;s behaviour with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.red-gate.com/products/reflector/&quot;&gt;Reflector&lt;/a&gt;, I discovered Microsoft use the SharedResourceProvider class in the Microsoft.Office.Server.Administration namespace. Who knows why, but this class is marked internal so reflection is required to access it, and therefore accessing it is not supported. We should be on relatively safe ground if MS products such as Project Server use it however&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following code retrieves the name of the SSP for the current site collection.
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;csharp&amp;#8217;]
SPSite site = SPContext.Current.Site;
ServerContext serverContext = ServerContext.GetContext(site);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PropertyInfo srpProp = serverContext.GetType().GetProperty(
	&amp;#8220;SharedResourceProvider&amp;#8221;,
	BindingFlags.NonPublic | BindingFlags.Instance);
object sharedResourceProvider = srpProp.GetValue(serverContext, null);
PropertyInfo srpName = sharedResourceProvider.GetType().GetProperty(
	&amp;#8220;Name&amp;#8221;,
	BindingFlags.Public | BindingFlags.Instance);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;string sspName = (string)srpName.GetValue(sharedResourceProvider, null);
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there the URL to the PSI web services within the SSP directly becomes the following (and the port number is always the following on every server):
http://&lt;em&gt;servername&lt;/em&gt;:56737/&lt;em&gt;SSPName&lt;/em&gt;/PSI/ or
https://&lt;em&gt;servername&lt;/em&gt;:56738/&lt;em&gt;SSPName&lt;/em&gt;/PSI/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does seem overly complex so if someone out there has a better solution please add it as a comment to this blog or update the &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/58809/retrieving-the-associated-shared-service-providers-name&quot;&gt;answer on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/10/programmatically-retrieving-the-name-of-an-ssp</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/10/programmatically-retrieving-the-name-of-an-ssp</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-10-14T15:51:37+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>SQL querying the queue</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently found myself in the situation where the Project Server queue service was taking up almost all of a server&amp;#8217;s CPU. Unfortunately due to the high demands of the queue jobs, the administration page was unavailable with a connection timeout error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to try and access the administration page again might have been to stop or restart the queue service or the entire server itself, but what if unpredictable behaviour had disrupted those jobs? Instead, by carefully looking at the Project Server databases we can see the draft project database stores a lot of information about the queue in tables and views starting with MSP_QUEUE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following query gives a summary of jobs in the queue:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;sql&amp;#8217;]
SELECT
  QPG.GRP_QUEUE_ID,
  QPG.CREATED_DATE,
  QPG.READY_FOR_PROCESSING_DATE,
  QPM.MSG_QUEUE_BODY_TYPE,
  QPG.GRP_QUEUE_MESSAGE_TYPE,
  QPG.GRP_QUEUE_STATE,
  QPG.PROCESSING_DATE,
  QPG.PERCENT_COMPLETE,
  QPG.COMPLETED_DATE,
  QPG.GRP_QUEUE_ERROR_INFO,
  QPG.GRP_QUEUE_PRIORITY,
  QPG.LAST_MSG_ID,
  QPG.LAST_ADMIN_ACTION
FROM dbo.MSP_QUEUE_PROJECT_GROUP_FULL_VIEW QPG (NOLOCK)
INNER JOIN dbo.MSP_QUEUE_PROJECT_MESSAGE QPM (NOLOCK)
  ON QPM.GRP_UID = QPG.GRP_UID
ORDER BY GRP_QUEUE_STATE DESC, GRP_QUEUE_PRIORITY, QPG.GRP_QUEUE_ID
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This query gives how many jobs are remaining to run:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;sql&amp;#8217;]
SELECT COUNT(*)
FROM dbo.MSP_QUEUE_PROJECT_GROUP_FULL_VIEW QPG (NOLOCK)
WHERE QPG.PROCESSING_DATE IS NULL
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This query gives how many jobs of each priority are remaining to run:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;sql&amp;#8217;]
SELECT QPG.GRP_QUEUE_PRIORITY, COUNT(*) AS [COUNT]
FROM dbo.MSP_QUEUE_PROJECT_GROUP_FULL_VIEW QPG (NOLOCK)
WHERE QPG.PROCESSING_DATE IS NULL
GROUP BY QPG.GRP_QUEUE_PRIORITY
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also an interesting statistics table, although I haven&amp;#8217;t yet found how to get a text value for GRP_QUEUE_MESSAGE_TYPE:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;sql&amp;#8217;]
SELECT QPS.*
FROM dbo.MSP_QUEUE_PROJECT_STATS QPS (NOLOCK)
[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally you would never want to execute raw SQL statements against the database, but as with any computer system, unpredictable things can happen. These queries might help with some troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/sql-querying-the-queue</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/sql-querying-the-queue</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-09-30T10:21:49+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Internal name vs display name</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Anyone that&amp;#8217;s done a reasonable amount of work with the SharePoint object model will soon come across its flaws. The one that I regularly come up against is when working with the SPField object that represents list columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are inconsistencies throughout the object model when attempting to retrieve an instance of an SPField, its value, or perform various other operations. In some cases the display name is required, or the internal name, or both! Even worse, rarely does the SDK document what is required to find your field. Unpredictable behaviour can also result in the cases where it checks for display name and internal name, because what if you have two fields with the same display name?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s just a few frustrating examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPFieldCollection.ContainsField:&lt;/strong&gt; Internal name &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; display name&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPFieldCollection.Item[string]:&lt;/strong&gt; Display name&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPViewFieldCollection.Exists:&lt;/strong&gt; Internal name&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom, another SharePoint developer, has made &lt;a href=&quot;http://tomblog.insomniacminds.com/2008/01/25/sharepoint-internals-internalname-versus-displayname/&quot;&gt;a list with more examples here&lt;/a&gt;. He also details the inconsistencies around when an exception is thrown - yet another place to get caught out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things in an API is consistency so it behaves like you would expect. I&amp;#8217;m sure how Microsoft can fix this without introducing breaking changes so maybe we will have to live with this for a long time yet. If in doubt, as always, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.red-gate.com/products/reflector/&quot;&gt;Reflector&lt;/a&gt; is your friend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/internal-name-vs-display-name</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/internal-name-vs-display-name</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-09-13T12:37:39+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Linking tasks to issues, risks, documents, and more...</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;In Project Server 2003 a feature was introduced to link issues, risks and documents to tasks. It&amp;#8217;s been carried over to 2007 as well (although the UI for it isn&amp;#8217;t as noticeable) and I think it&amp;#8217;s one of the coolest yet underrated features in the web interface. Let me take you through it&amp;#8230; (Note: you will need the Create Object Link category permission to use this feature.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every project workspace out of the box comes with the Project Documents, Risks and Issues lists. On the add and edit pages of these lists, you can find &amp;#8220;Link Items&amp;#8221;:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/link-items-link.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking Link Items while creating or editing an issue, for example, allows the issue to be linked to any task in the project. Also, this linking can have several meanings, such as whether the issue simply relates to the task, affects the task, or whether the task resolves the issue. Here is the dialog:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/link-task-to-issue.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll notice the drop-down at the top that reads Project Tasks. This can be changed so that this issue is linked to any risk, document or other issue as well! (Note there is no additional &amp;#8216;meaning&amp;#8217; unless linking to a task.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon clicking OK on this dialog box, a nice little summary is displayed of the link options chosen:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/link-task-to-issue-summary.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the issues list is just an example here. It is also possible to link items from the other lists previously mentioned. Here are the other dialog boxes shown&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/link-task-to-risk.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Document:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/09/link-task-to-document.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linking&amp;#8217;s cool, but now what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously whenever you look at a linked object you will be able to see and click on what each object is linked to which helps to describe the relations within your project, not to mention handy as well. Some examples are linking a document to a task for its delivery, or linking a risk item to a risky task! Also very useful is that the link gets propagated to the reporting database when the workspace&amp;#8217;s project is next published, so some neat queries can be written to relate your data together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s even better is what you don&amp;#8217;t see. This functionality is powered by the Object Link Provider, which is described in some detail within the &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa568840.aspx&quot;&gt;Project 2007 SDK&lt;/a&gt;. With some custom development work, it is possible to link tasks or project workspace items in other lists to any object you can reach with a URL. Imagine the possibilities - linking to an item in the company&amp;#8217;s financial system, for example! This can all be done with the ObjectLinkProvider web service (examine the SDK for more details).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A few cautionary words&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have already encountered, some functionality in Project Server can break when you start altering project workspaces. This is even though it does nothing to stop you and virtually every customer/user has a requirement to. The Link Items feature is no exception here. If you delete the Links column from a workspace, there is no way I&amp;#8217;ve found to put it back (this is probably because it is not a built-in SharePoint field type). Instead, try setting it to Hidden within the content type! In fact, hiding the field in the list&amp;#8217;s content type should be done for every workspace field you don&amp;#8217;t want to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this provides a deeper look at a feature that doesn&amp;#8217;t seem to get mentioned much. If you have good uses for &amp;#8220;Link Items&amp;#8221;, please add a few comments to this post!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/linking-tasks-to-issues-risks-documents-and-more</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/linking-tasks-to-issues-risks-documents-and-more</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-09-10T15:14:55+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>SharePoint and SQL schemas</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m just under two weeks away from installing the infrastructure update to a production environment. But of course these things need testing first so I started the install on the development environment. Thing&amp;#8217;s went hairy for a while&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I must admit I&amp;#8217;m not running the update as the service account, &lt;a href=&quot;http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc671413.aspx&quot;&gt;recommended by Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;. This is because I&amp;#8217;m working in a locked down environment where trying to get the permission to do this requires a lot of questions, moaning and red tape. However both my account and the service account (there&amp;#8217;s only one service account in use here) are local administrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The log file pointed to by the SharePoint Configuration Wizard contains this ever so helpful line: &amp;#8220;An exception of type Microsoft.SharePoint.PostSetupConfiguration.PostSetupConfigurationTaskException was thrown.  Additional exception information: Failed to upgrade SharePoint Products and Technologies.&amp;#8221; However, with a little more digging there are details located at C:\Program Files\Common Files\Microsoft Shared\web server extensions\12\LOGS. (This isn&amp;#8217;t actually the folder where I have directed diagnostic logs to, but for the purposes of an upgrade it seems SharePoint sometimes redirects it!) The logs contain errors over the several times I tried to upgrade&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgrade.log:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SqlException: The default schema does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SqlException: Cannot find the object &amp;#8216;MFN_Epm_GetAllCustomFieldsInformation&amp;#8217;, because it does not exist or you do not have permission.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SqlException: Cannot drop the function &amp;#8216;dbo.MFN_Epm_GetAllCustomFieldsInformation&amp;#8217;, because it does not exist or you do not have permission.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in the ULS logs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The schema version (3.1.4.0) of the database SharePoint_AdminContent on server_x is not consistent with the expected database schema version (3.1.5.0) on server_x.  Connections to this database from this server have been blocked to avoid data loss.  Upgrade the web front end or the content database to ensure that these versions match.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SqlException: Cannot find the user &amp;#8216;DOMAIN\myusername&amp;#8217;, because it does not exist or you do not have permission.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Queue unable to interact with SQL. Queue type (Project Queue, Timesheet Queue etc): ProjectQ Exception: Microsoft.Office.Project.Server.BusinessLayer.Queue.QueueSqlException: PeriodicTasks failed &amp;#8212;&amp;gt; System.Data.SqlClient.SqlException: Invalid object name &amp;#8216;MSP_QUEUE_RENDEZVOUS&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that I don&amp;#8217;t have permission to the databases. However, my account is db_owner on every database The service account permissions haven&amp;#8217;t been changed. What&amp;#8217;s going on?!! It turns out the root of the cause was described this exception: &lt;strong&gt;The default schema does not exist&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know a great deal about the schema feature introduced with SQL 2005, however with every user added to a SQL 2005 box, an accompanying schema with the same name is also created. A colleague of mine who was doing some spring cleaning on our databases removed the schema for our service account, however the service account&amp;#8217;s SQL user was still trying to use it as its default schema! The solution was to change the schema to &lt;strong&gt;dbo&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the upgrade still didn&amp;#8217;t quite complete since I was part of the way through the upgrade when it fell over&amp;#8230; I also had to create a fake MFN_Epm_GetAllCustomFieldsInformation function in the Reporting database so the upgrade could find and drop it (fortunately replaced with the new version in the upgrade).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a big relief that this ended up working. The downside is that my user account and a schema for it have been created on the database server. It can&amp;#8217;t be removed right now because the new database objects that come with the update have my schema set as their owner! Now I have to change them all&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/sharepoint-and-sql-schemas</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/09/sharepoint-and-sql-schemas</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-09-03T16:57:17+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Project Server ItemSwapper control</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ItemSwapper hasn&amp;#8217;t been documented by Microsoft so its behaviour may change between service packs - use at your own risk!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the 2007 version, Project Server is now a SharePoint application. One of the best things about this is the nifty stuff you get out of the box as part of SP. Custom controls are a highlight, of which there are many that can be used in your custom Project Server solutions. Even better is that Project Server 2007 comes with some cool controls of its own which you can use in any solution running within Project Server. My latest discovery is the handy &lt;strong&gt;ItemSwapper&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;#8221;attachment_29&amp;#8221; align=&amp;#8221;aligncenter&amp;#8221; width=&amp;#8221;510&amp;#8221; caption=&amp;#8221;ItemSwapper&amp;#8221;]&lt;a href=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/07/itemswapper-intro.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexangas.files.wordpress.com/2008/07/itemswapper-intro.png&quot; alt=&quot;ItemSwapper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might look familiar to you from popular administration pages such as &amp;#8220;Manage Queue&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Manage Groups&amp;#8221;. Just by popping one of these on your page, you get a pretty flawless interface to selecting projects. It&amp;#8217;s also speedy and has some great features both client and server side. It&amp;#8217;s great to use in a web part used for selecting report parameters, so that&amp;#8217;s what we&amp;#8217;re going to build in this post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, let&amp;#8217;s have a look at two other custom controls used by ItemSwapper. There is the ItemSwapperLabel (extended from System.Web.UI.WebControls.Label) which renders the text above each list, and ItemSwapperSelect (extended from System.Web.UI.HtmlControls.HtmlSelect) which renders the list itself. Data binding is done with ItemSwapperSelect and the &amp;#8216;parent&amp;#8217; ItemSwapper control renders all of these controls for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ItemSwapper control refers to the two select lists as the &amp;#8216;alpha&amp;#8217; and &amp;#8216;beta&amp;#8217; lists (originally designed for Greek Project Server?). In our example the beta list will be blank for us to add projects into, so we only want to initalise the alpha list. Looking at the code, our CreateChildControls method contains:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;csharp&amp;#8217;]protected override void CreateChildControls()
{
    alphaSelect = new ItemSwapperSelect();
    alphaSelect.Multiple = true;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;projectSwapper = new ItemSwapper();
projectSwapper.ID = &quot;projectSwapper&quot;;
projectSwapper.TrackBetaListChanges = true;
projectSwapper.AlphaSelect = alphaSelect;
projectSwapper.LblAlphaList.Text = &quot;Available Projects&quot;;
projectSwapper.LblBetaList.Text = &quot;Selected Projects&quot;;
projectSwapper.DisplaySelectedItemText = false;
projectSwapper.ShowBetaUpDownButtons = true;
projectSwapper.ShowRestoreAllButton = true;
projectSwapper.ShowRemoveAllButton = true;
this.Controls.Add(projectSwapper); }[/sourcecode]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be pretty self-explanatory (we will discuss the ID and TrackBetaListChanges properties later in this post). Now let&amp;#8217;s perform a data bind in our OnLoad method:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;csharp&amp;#8217;]protected override void OnLoad(EventArgs e)
{
    if (!Page.IsPostBack)
    {
        DataTable projects = DataLayer.GetProjects();
        projectSwapper.DataSource = projects;
        projectSwapper.DataTextField = &amp;#8220;Name&amp;#8221;;
        projectSwapper.DataValueField = &amp;#8220;Uid&amp;#8221;;
    }
}[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will now render fine, but the finishing touch is a workaround to what I would call a bug. If you set ShowRestoreAllButton to true, this will display the &amp;#8220;Add All&amp;#8221; button. However it is important to know that this button is greyed out unless the user has selected an item first, meaning that will need two clicks to add all projects to the other list. I don&amp;#8217;t know why Microsoft would have done this, but to get around it, add the following code to our OnPreRender method:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;csharp&amp;#8217;]protected override void OnPreRender(EventArgs e)
{
    alphaSelect.SelectedIndex = 0;
}[/sourcecode]
Have a look at the work so far as the ItemSwapper should now render!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;#8217;s make use of the items chosen in the lists. First of all we&amp;#8217;ll need a button in our web part for users to click on and start the report generation. We&amp;#8217;ll also need at least one hidden field that will contain the selected items for us to use on the server side. Note that there is quite a bit of data we can get from the ItemSwapper JavaScript object, such as a count of items for both lists, text labels of chosen items for both lists, and values (e.g. project GUIDs) of chosen items for both lists!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to do retrieve the data on the client side there are two key properties we need to set when creating the ItemSwapper which I touched upon earlier: ID and TrackBetaListChanges (or if you care about the alpha list, TrackAlphaListChanges). We need to use JavaScript to get a reference to the ItemSwapper object and setting ID lets us use document.getElementByID() to do this. (Surprisingly and fortunately, ID doesn&amp;#8217;t get mangled in usual SharePoint fashion when rendered.) Setting TrackBetaListChanges sets a property on the JavaScript object to, well, track beta list changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So going back to CreateChildControls(), let&amp;#8217;s add the following code and connect our server code to the client:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;csharp&amp;#8217;]chosenProjectValues = new HiddenField();
this.Controls.Add(chosenProjectValues);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;createButton = new Button();
createButton.Text = &amp;#8220;Create&amp;#8221;;
createButton.Click += CreateButton_Click;  // server-side processing done in this method
createButton.OnClientClick = String.Format(&amp;#8220;SaveItemSwapperValues(&amp;#8216;{0}&amp;#8217;, &amp;#8216;{1}&amp;#8217;);&amp;#8221;, projectSwapper.ID, chosenProjectValues.ClientID);
this.Controls.Add(createButton);[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything&amp;#8217;s ready now on the server side. We just need to create the SaveItemSwapperValues JavaScript function. Put this JavaScript wherever is standard for your projects.
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;jscript&amp;#8217;]function SaveItemSwapperValues(itemSwapperClientID, chosenValuesClientID)
{
    var chosenValuesField = document.getElementById(chosenValuesClientID);
    var itemSwapper = document.getElementById(itemSwapperClientID);
    chosenValuesField.value = itemSwapper.GetBetaListValuesAsString();
}[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it! Now when your server-code hits CreateButton_Click(), you should find a nice comma-separated list of project GUIDs in the Value property of your hidden field that can be used to generate reports!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#8217;s nice to take things a bit further&amp;#8230; Our Create button is always active, even when no projects are in the chosen list. Well then, behold! The ItemSwapper contains JavaScript event handling functionality! Add script that runs on startup such as this:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;jscript&amp;#8217;]var itemSwapper = document.getElementById(&amp;#8216;projectSwapper&amp;#8217;); // &amp;#8216;projectSwapper&amp;#8217; should be passed as a parameter and not hard-coded
itemSwapper.OnAlphaListChange = ChosenProjectsChanged;
itemSwapper.OnBetaListChange = ChosenProjectsChanged;[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then add the following with the SaveItemSwapperValues function:
[sourcecode language=&amp;#8217;jscript&amp;#8217;]function ChosenProjectsChanged()
{
    var itemSwapper = document.getElementById(&amp;#8216;projectSwapper&amp;#8217;);
    var createButton = /* how you get this reference depends on your environment */
    if (itemSwapper.betaListItemCount == 0)
    {
        createButton.disabled = true;
    }
    else
    {
        createButton.disabled = false;
    }
}[/sourcecode]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;#8217;re talkin&amp;#8217; - a smart ItemSwapper. And that&amp;#8217;s not all, there is heaps of handy JavaScript goodness you can hook on to if you&amp;#8217;re able to navigate to this file and have a look: C:\Program Files\Common Files\Microsoft Shared\web server extensions\12\TEMPLATE\LAYOUTS\PWA\LIBRARY\ItemSwapper.htc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, none of the ItemSwapper controls are sealed so you are free to extend them with your own functionality!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/07/project-server-itemswapper-control</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/07/project-server-itemswapper-control</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-07-28T20:00:22+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Intro</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there! I&amp;#8217;m Alex, working on SharePoint and Project Server and based in London. I&amp;#8217;ve been working with SharePoint and Project Server since the 2003 versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is intended to provide discoveries and thoughts from working with these technologies. I hope you find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/02/intro</link>
                <guid>http://alexangas.github.io/blog/2008/02/intro</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-02-14T18:03:55+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>


</channel>
</rss>
